Finding Aid for Charles Edwin Kent papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Edwin Kent papers
1944-1990
1957-1980
Kent, Charles Edwin.
2013111 Aa 2
Charles Edwin Kent, a resident of Ann Arbor, Michigan, worked as an engineer, solving complex technological problems for Bendix Corporation for most of his career, first in the Systems Division, and later in the Aerospace Systems Division. Kent worked on automotive, communications, weaponry, and space research, as well as a number of other subjects. The collection encompasses material primarily from his college years through his career. The series in the collection are Personal Files and Professional Files. Papers primarily include research notes, internal company memorandums, and research reports.
7.5 linear feet in 8 boxes including oversize
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection donated by Charles E. Kent (Donor no. 9756 ) in October 2012 and April 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Charles Edwin Kent was born in Augusta, Michigan on May 21, 1928. He attended the University of Michigan where he received a Bachelors of Science degree in Electrical Engineering. In 1952 he married Nancy L. Hutchinson; they had two children and resided in Ann Arbor.
Kent's career began working as a Project Engineer at the U.S. Army Signal Corps Engineering Laboratories from 1951 to 1957. In 1957 he accepted a job working at the Bendix Corporation as a Senior Engineer and Acting Department Head in the Systems Division. However, he left the company in 1962 and began working at Datronics Engineering, Inc. as an Assistant to the Assistant General Manager. Charles Kent returned to Bendix Corporation in 1964 as a Principal Engineer and Program Manager of the Aerospace Systems Division, and in 1974, he became Corporate Director in Engineering Problem Analysis.
Charles Edwin Kent specialized in analyzing complex problems, especially those which required immediate solutions. One example of this work is the APOLLO Lunar Surface Experiments (ALSEP) New Technology report that he executed in only 10 days in April, 1967 while working at Bendix Corporation. Kent's efforts on this report saved the company from defaulting on their contract with NASA.
The Charles Edwin Kent papers are comprised of materials documenting his professional and personal life.
Subjects:
Kent, Charles Edwin.; Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package.; Bendix Corporation. Aerospace Systems Division.; Engineering--Research--Michigan.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Strand Engineering Company.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal Files
  The Personal Files series (1.5 linear feet) includes information about Kent's hometown of Augusta, Michigan. Materials include Augusta newspapers mentioning the Kent family and Augusta bicentennial publications. There is also a focus on Kent's years at Augusta High School and the University of Michigan. Two scrapbooks, one of Charles' and one of his wife, Nancy's, provide information about their social lives and accomplishments while in school. There are also college course materials, including textbooks, primarily from the college of engineering, as well as University of Michigan magazines and football publications. Also of note and biographical importance are resumes and detailed descriptions of his work experience written by Kent.
  - Augusta, MI history, 1985 (Box 1)
    (Newspapers, bicentennial publications)
  - Nancy L. [nee Hutchinson] Kent (Box 1)
  - Job search materials
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Resume, 1962 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    - College of Engineering
      - Writing and drawing practice (Box 1)
      - Drawing One, 1947 (Box 8)
    - Course materials, 1946-1949 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-1958 (Box 1)
    - Publications, 1947-1951 (Box 1)
      (The Michigan Technic Magazine, Gargoyle Magazine, and three University of Michigan football programs)
    - Scrapbooks (Box 8)
      - Charles Kent, Augusta High School and University of Michigan, 1944-1951 (Box 8)
      - Nancy L. Hutchinson, University of Michigan., 1948-1952 (Box 8)
  - Work experience, 1961-1982 (Box 1)
    (List of projects Kent worked on at Bendix Corp. from 1974-1979 descriptions of career work experience, resumes, and letter of resignation from 1961)
- Professional Files
  The Professional Files (6.6 linear feet) series is divided into materials from Bendix Corporation and Strand Engineering Company. Strand Engineering Company was owned by Datronics Engineering, Inc. This series focuses on the research, projects, and policies Kent was involved in working with during his engineering career at Bendix Corporation and Strand Engineering Co. Many of these papers are internal company memorandums, research notes, and bound reports. The chronological files created by Kent, which he divided and dated by year from 1974-1982, contain information regarding his projects and monthly activity reports, primarily in the form of internal memorandums.
  - Bendix Corporation
    - Annual reports and insurance, 1961-1973; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - APOLLO Lunar Surface Experiments Package (ALSEP) New Technology report, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Bendix and University of Michigan space technology press, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Bendix Update, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
      (photographs)
    - Bx 2000 quality investigation, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - Chronological files
      - May-December, 1974 (Box 2)
      - 1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976 (Box 2)
      - 1977 (Box 2)
      - 1978 (Box 2)
      - 1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980 (Box 2)
      - 1982 (Box 2)
    - Company stock, 1971; 1980 (Box 2)
    - Corning Glass Works, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Design reviews, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Engineer classes and salaries, 1963-1970 (Box 2)
    - Engineering organization audit, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Future planning, 1964-1970 (Box 2)
    - History, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Kent
      - Goals, 1974-1980 (Box 2)
      - Job description, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
      - Performance reports, 1962-1970 (Box 2)
      - Responsibilities, goals, and objectives, 1966-1972 (Box 2)
      - To-do lists and notes, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Memorandums (Box 3)
      - 1974-1982 (Box 3)
      - Dr. J. W. Weil, 1974-1982 (Box 3)
    - Monthly reports, 1974-1982 (Box 3)
    - Metric guidance manual, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Metrication, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
    - Microprocessor conference, October, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967-1980 (Box 3)
    - Patents, 1969-1972 (Box 3)
    - Product integrity policy II, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - Product liability
      - Advisory group, circa 1979 (Box 3)
      - Corporate policy, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
      - Policy, 1979 (Box 3)
      - Reference material, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
    - Project audit procedure, 1974-1982 (Box 3)
    - Project reviews
      - Air Brake, Adaptive Breaking System (ABS), 1975-1976 (Box 3)
      - Constant frequency generator, 1977 (Box 3)
      - Communications, navigation, and identification, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Electronic turbine engine control, 1976 (Box 3)
      - GM robotic paint spray system, 1976 (Box 3)
      - —8, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Patents, 1969-1972 (Box 3)
      - Policy, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Policy and procedure, circa 1978 (Box 3)
      - Programmable Assembly Cybernation System (PACS), undated (Box 3)
    - Publications, 1961-1977 (Box 3)
    - Research
      - ADVENT, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Air weather service, 1958 (Box 4)
      - AJ-Automatic Frequency Control (AFC), 1959 (Box 4)
      - APOLLO, undated (Box 4)
      - Asbestos, 1979-1990 (Box 4)
      - Automobile EPA certification tests, 1974-1981 (Box 4)
      - Automotive Engine Control (AEC), 1976 (Box 4)
      - B-70 communications subsystem, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Camera system, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Communication links hardening, undated (Box 4)
      - Communications satellite systems, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Data compression, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Drawing and designs, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Film scanner design, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Earth resource remote sensing, 1969-1972 (Box 4)
      - Earth resource technology satellite, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Electronic scanner, 1962 (Box 4)
      - Electronics control unit, 1975 (Box 4)
      - EMP simulation, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Gravitational models, 1972-1974 (Box 4)
      - High voltage generators, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Injector techniques, 1975 (Box 4)
      - Interpolation, 1972 (Box 4)
      - M and TC equipment, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Mailbuoy, 1961 (Box 4)
      - Microwave hazards, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
      - Minuteman weapon system, 1959 (Box 4)
      - Miniature ICBM, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 1960-1982 (Box 4)
      - Modulation and detection, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Multispectral picture registration, 1969 (Box 4)
      - NIMBUS, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Position Fixing and Navigation Systems (PFNS), 1963 (Box 4)
      - Radio frequency, 1974 (Box 4)
      - RBV camera, Image Motion Compensation (IMC), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Receiver designs, undated (Box 4)
      - Reports (Box 5)
        - 1958-1973, 3 folders (Box 5)
        - Data compression, 1972 (Box 5)
        - Night vision augmentation for light aircraft, 1967 (Box 5)
      - Requests for Newland and Kent paper, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
      - Stirling engine, 1974-1976 (Box 5)
      - UGO-Antarctic automated stations, 1972 (Box 5)
      - UNICOM, 1959 (Box 5)
      - Vela hotel, 1961 (Box 5)
      - X-rays (Box 5)
    - Ricardo meeting, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Technology, undated (Box 5)
    - Written Works
      - APOLLO Lunar Surface Experiments New Technology Report, 1967 (Box 5)
      - Corporate Independent Research & Development (IR&D) plans, 1964-1972 (Box 5)
      - Final reports, 1961-1974 (Box 5)
      - Kent and Newland paper, 1960 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1958-1974 (Box 6)
      - Printed Circuit Board Design Guide, 1978 (Box 6)
      - Printed Circuit Board Manufacturing, 1978 (Box 6)
      - Proposals, 1959-1970 (Box 6)
      - Reports, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Reports, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Satellite Communication Program, 1960 (Box 7)
  - Strand Engineering Company
    (owned by Datronics Engineering, Inc.)
    - Burroughs Corporation light problem, 1962 (Box 7)
    - Command destruct, 1961 (Box 7)
    - Displays, 1960-1962 (Box 7)
    - Expense accounts, 1962; 1973 (Box 7)
Related material
The Kent family papers, 1855-1969 (call number 0691 Aa 2) includes a journal that documents farming activities and expense accounts, family photographs, and miscellaneous other family materials (about 0.5 linear feet), all from Augusta, Michigan where the family has resided since the mid-1800s.
Finding aid can be found at the Bentley Historical Library.